What exactly is communication?
The most simple definition: Communication is
each act of transmitting information.
Information in the broadest sense of the word:
including thoughts, ideas and emotions.
Giving someone a bouquet of flowers is
communicating a certain message.
Adding to that gift a verbal compliment,
"You're pretty" is another separate act of
communication.
Blushing 'because you've just received flowers
and a compliment
is again another form of communication.
As social animals we communicate day in day
out...
with spoken words, non-verbal gestures, signs
and symbols.
Sometimes we use media to communicate a
message.
Media are the channels that we use to
communicate.
Scholars don’t really agree on the definition of
the word media.
Television, internet, radio, mobile phones, the
soapbox we stand on to give a speech,
they are all technical media in a way. Things we
constructed to amplify our communication.
In the more broader definition, we can include
our hands, voice and eyes,
that we all use to communicate somehow, in the
list of communication channels, of media.
In general however, whenever we discuss
mediated communication
or the mass media, we only mean the first
category.
Over the years scientists from different scientific
disciplines have studied these channels
of communication and all these different forms
that communication can take.
The results of their studies have formed the
basis of the relatively new
'science of communication'.
Even today, many scholars in other disciplines
study the exact same communication
phenomena as we do.
We share theories, models and often use the
same methods to analyse & describe our field.
It is therefore useful to be aware of how these
other disciplines are connected with ours.
To get an idea of the different levels of
communication
and how they are connected to other scientific
disciplines,
we can look at the so-called pyramid of
communication.
On the highest level of this pyramid we find
societal communication,
which is by its very nature aimed at a large
mass audience.
Therefore mainly historians, political scientists
and sociologists studied this perspective.
Under that is the level of institutional
communication,
that is performed by political parties, organized
religions, large corporations and such.
Then comes the level of group communication.
Groups are audiences that feel a high level of
group identification,
for instance a family or a fanclub.
Both institutional and group communication are
in the field of sociology
and cultural anthropology.
We have now arrived to the level of interpersonal
communication,
basically the communication between two or
more people.
Both sociologists and psychologists study this
field.
Finally there is the level of intrapersonal
communication.
This would be the communication you have with
yourself.
With this we mean all information processing,
thinking, internalizing information
and the process of giving meaning to the world
around us.
And of course this approach leans heavily on the
discipline of psychology.