Welcome in week 2 of our MOOC.
I hope you've enjoyed our format. I also hope
you've done some of the self-evaluation tests
that we made available and checked out the
further readings section in the online portal.
Since we only discuss most theories very
briefly, this is a good chance to explore them
further.
Also, visit the forum. I'll often help out by posting
answers to recurring questions here.
And let us know what you think of our MOOC.
All feedback is welcome.
This week we’re going to talk about the history
of communication science
and I’d like to stress that last part.
Because we’re going to talk about when people
started talking
and especially writing about communication.
So even though we could talk for hours about
the presumed communication methods of
prehistoric man and ancient civilizations after
that,
about the earliest forms of communication,
theories on the development of language,
the introduction of mediated communication,
through symbolism in rock art and figurines and
such,
we are not going to do so.
We are not going to discuss the oldest musical
instruments or the first writing we’ve found,
nor the power of communication through
architecture and useable items like coins.
Почему?
Because we have no record that these
civilizations thought
about communication on a meta level
and constructed theories about it’s existence or
use.
Instead we’re going to start our journey here in
Ancient Greece.
Because the writings of the Ancient Greeks and
after that the Romans
are the oldest books about our topic to survive.
After covering the earliest Communication
Science of the Greeks and Romans
we’ll talk about Medieval times.
A time when there was little to no
Communication Science.
Then we'll discuss the printing revolution and the
Renaissance of our field.
We’ll end this week's MOOC with the nineteenth
century,
industrialization, political change and the
changing communication landscape.
Next week we’ll continue with twentieth century
communication theory.