In the previous section we discussed the printing
revolution.
Shortly after the innovations by Gutenberg,
millions and later billions of printed copies
spread out through Europe.
Not only books rolled of the presses.
Especially short books and leaflets, collectively
named pamphlets,
were printed to entertain, persuade and inform
readers.
From the sixteenth century these pamphlets
were in many ways the new mass medium,
giving information and opinion on current affairs,
spreading the news
and commentary on that news throughout
Europe.
It was through pamphlets that many religious
and political debates were fought out.
It was pamphlets that informed multitudes about
great military victories and defeats,
about the gossip that surrounded the European
royal houses.
Pamphlets had many styles. They could be
serious or very funny.
They were written for the learned and those who
could hardly read, and everyone in between.
In sixteenth century Venice the first newspaper
was published,
and quickly after this also German, Dutch and
English newspapers appeared.
But these newspapers didn’t reach a mass
audience,
as they remained for a long time a medium for
the elite,
with a small readership and focus on foreign
political news.
Pamphlets, however, discussed foremost
domestic and even local news.
Readership could be quite high and there is a lot
of evidence that suggests
they were read out loud in market places and in
taverns for people who couldn’t read.
Illustrations and attention gaining covers further
added to their popular appeal.
This graph shows that, in the Dutch Republic,
every newsworthy event or crisis was
accompanied by hundreds of pamphlets.
The first peaks are important moments in the
Eighty-Years War (1568-1648)
in which the Dutch won their independence from
Spain. Later we see that hundreds of pamphlets
were published when the Republic was attacked
from three sides,
By France, Münster and Cologne at the same
time in 1672.
A hateful pamphlet campaign put the blame at
the feet of two leading politicians,
which led to their deaths at a public lynching.
Historical evidence suggests that political
enemies of these politicians
were actually behind the smear campaign that
led to their deaths.
Examples like these showed contemporary
scholars the powers of mass communication.
It clearly paid off to heed public opinion and to
be able to use mass media
like the influential pamphlet press. Scholars like
Niccolò Machiavelli
approached the topic of mass communication
from this political power angle,
using elements from antiquity and combining
these with new ideas.
This approach was the starting point of a truly
modern communication science.
We’ll look at how that evolved in the next and
final section of this week.