Earlier I pointed towards World War II as a
reason for the popular and scientific reluctance
to accept a minimal effect conclusion.
A second reason was the arrival of television in
the 1950s and 1960s as a new medium
with even more power of attraction than its
predecessors
The effects of television were presumed huge,
but not in the old 'magic bullet' way.
Not so much direct, short term, and uniform, but
1) Long term, with repeated exposure.
One new theory called cultivation proposed that
after repeated long term exposure
audiences tend to shift towards the dominant
media viewpoints on matters.
2) Indirect effects, much more attention was
given now to
indirect effects like associated effects.
For instance, when we see a commercial of a
muscular man eating ice cream we might not
run in to the shop to immediately buy ice cream.
But perhaps after several commercials like this,
we will associate this particular brand with a
healthy appearance,
thereby increasing the likelihood that we’ll prefer
this brand.
These types of effects are also typically longer
lasting that the magic bullet
and hypodermic needle effects.
3) Personal effects. Now it was appreciated that
one audience member
is not the same as the other.
Effects therefore are pluriform and have to be
studied in context. A violent cartoon
might have a completely different effect on a
child that watches it alone
than on a child that watches it with siblings or
parents.
4) Reinforcement rather than change.
Studies increasingly indicate that reinforcement
effects are quite strong,
people remember and process content
selectively,
based on their own knowledge and
predispositions.
Therefore things that connect with their preferred
reality will sooner be processed.
A topic that we’ll discuss more in length in the
next week by the way.
Television was in many ways a new platform:
it captivated its audience, created new worlds
within a media reality.
Television shows had a huge impact. Unlike the
paper, people watched television together,
so in many ways it was a social medium as
well.
It was also topic for discussion.
You could quickly isolate yourself if you weren’t
aware of new programs and shows on television.
Hypermediality, when people reference media
content,
became one way of opening yourself up or
closing yourself of to a group.
We can imagine the new co-worker
who is the only one who hasn’t seen a new
series on television.
He’ll probably feel as though he’s less part of
the group now.
And you know, to some extent, this is true.
Television became a preferred way to spend
time, alone or together.
Shows and series were a way to identify
yourself, as an audience member
or even as a fan of that particular program
Social Learning, when people learn skills or how
to behave in situations in a social setting,
proved to be quite effective through television.
Even though I have never been in a fire, I have
some idea what to do and avoid,
because of many movies and series. If these
ideas are correct of course, remains to be seen,
but I do have some inkling based on media
exposure.
Just like I think I know what to expect in a
courtroom, space shuttle, or dinosaur attack.
Not because of direct experience, but through
mediated experience.
Other scholars established Socialization Effects
for television.
Socialization is when we learn norms and values
in a informal way.
Just like we learn from our parents, family, and
friends, we learn from television as well.
All of these effects were probably not unique for
television compared to other media,
but they were very apparent in television.
It was probably the rise of television more than
anything that caused the final paradigm,
a compromise between minimal and powerful
effects.
This is the dominant paradigm of today, that of
negotiated media effects.