--- Жирный, курсив, подчеркнутый, зачеркнутый , большой шрифт
First sequence for translation test. 
--- заголовок
Second sequence for translation test. 
--- Жирный+курсив, жирный, курсив, подчеркнутый курсив, зачеркнутый
Third sequence for translation test. 
--- Жирная строка
Almost last sequence ... for translation test. 
--- Строка курсив
Last sequence for translation test. 
First sequence for translation test. 
Second sequence for translation test. 
--- Жирный на всю строку + курсив на 1 слове
Third sequence for translation test. 
--- Чистая строка с пробелами
Almost last sequence       for translation test. 
--- Каждое слово больше предыдущего по шрифту
Last sequence for 1st translation test. 
