We’ve just seen that different scientific
disciplines all study communication.
Of course they focus on different aspects of
communication.
Some scholars want to understand the workings
of the media infrastructure for instance,
others focus on the social importance of
communication, or
political communication effects or one of many
alternative perspectives.
It’s not surprising that communication is studied
by so many from so many angles.
It fills our lives & society, we spend tremendous
amounts of time communicating ideas,
sharing thoughts, absorbing new information,
being entertained or persuaded somehow.
Communication, simply put, enables us to
function as social, cultural and political animals.
It makes sense that these different perspectives
have led to a wide spectrum
of scientific thought on the topic of
communication.
In this course we’ll go out and explore some of
them and try to find our way
in this wild jumble of theories, models and
concepts.
Perhaps a good starting point therefore is to
begin with a brief definition
of ‘theory’, ‘model’, and ‘concept’.
A concept is a word or set of words that
represents an idea.
It’s of course important to clearly define the
concepts we use.
Let’s take the concept of ‘identity’ for instance.
It’s easy to imagine two or more different
interpretations
about what constitutes an identity
Is it how one views oneself, or perhaps we
should also take into consideration
how one's identity is perceived by others.
Or is that particular concept better described
perhaps with the word ‘image’?
Often scientists squabble over definitions, and
rightly so,
because it should be clear what we talk about.
These discussions sometimes never stop, and
why would they?
Different people give different meanings to a
word,
and who can say which are the ‘right’ or ‘wrong’
definitions?
At most we can speak about preferred or
dominant definitions of concepts,
but even these usually change over time and
from context to context.
In this course I will often stop to define certain
key concepts.
I would like to stipulate that these definitions are
unfortunately
more often than not quite disputed.
If you are following this MOOC and you had
some previous classes in communication
or perhaps you have worked in communication
or read books or articles about the topic
don’t be surprised when I will define things
slightly differently than you have learned.
For instance, when I said that media are every
channel that we use to communicate,
so this would include the voice, it’s very possible
that you have learned previously
that only technical channels are considered
media, which would exclude the voice.
Because both definitions, and many more, exist
in the scientific field.
To make things more difficult, scientists, like
many professionals,
sometimes give every day words a different
meaning.
If I would ask a random person in the street the
definition of the word ‘text’,
most will agree that a ‘text’ is a message made
up out of some type of letters.
Communication scientists however regard each
carrier of communication as a text.
So a movie, a song, a painting, they‘re all ‘texts’
in our eyes, ready to be ‘read’ by an audience.