Okay, so in this next segment of the
class, we're going to talk about how to
decode with phrase-based translation
models.
That is, how we actually apply
phrase-based translation models to new
sentences to produce translations.
So to recap, the critical ideal in a
phase-based model is the idea of a
phrase-based lexicon.
So, a phrase-based lexicon contains
phrase entries f, e.
So these are pairs, where each f is a
sequence of one or more foreign, foreign
words, and each e is a sequence of one or
more English words.
So, if we look at this particular German
sentence, we shall use as an example
throughout these slides.
and say we want to translate that into
English, then the phrase-based lexicon is
going to provide various entries which
may be relevant to this particular
sentence.
So here are some example entries in the
lexicon, we might say, these two words in
German correspond to we must or maybe
these three words in German correspond to
we must also.
So we have the first two words here and
the first three words here.
This single word in German, which appears
here, might be translated as seriously,
so these are three entries from the
phrased-based lexicon.
In practice, a lexicon might have, you
know, millions of entries.
And we saw in the last lecture segment
how we can extract these kinds of
lexicons from large quantities of
translation examples, by first running
the IBM translation models to derive
alignments, and then based on those
alignments, pulling out these phrase
based entries.
I'll use g of f, e to refer to the score
for lexicon entry.
So each of these has a score.
And I wouldn't mind having minus 1.5
here, minus 1.8 here, minus 0.2 here.
so for example, this might be the log of
the ratio of accounts.
This is very similar to maximum
likelihood estimate, this could be
thought of as t of f given e with the
conditional probability of the foreign
sequence of words, f condition on the
English sentence sequence of words e
ratio of these two counts.
And we're going to take the log of this
as we saw in the last lecture, it's
convenient to take logs, and then, we'll
start summing these different scores for
different phrases used in the
translation.
So throughout this lecture, I'm going to
consider phrase-based models consist of
three things.
So firstly, a phrase-based lexicon
consisting of f, e pairs, exactly as I
just showed you, the second thing we're
going to make use of is a trigram
language model for the language which
we're trying to translate into.
So throughout this lecture, I'll assume
that we're trying to translate from
German into English.
And so, we have these phrase entries as
one component.
The second component is a trigram
language model for English.
So we have a language model, for example,
a trigram language model for the language
into which we're trying to translate.
So this will have parameters exactly as
we saw in the first lecture of this
class, for example, parameters such as
the probability of also, given that the
previous two words were we and must.
And finally, we're going to have a
distortion parameter.
This is a single parameter, this is
typically negative.
And as we'll see, this will penalize
things from moving too far in the
translation process, when we start to use
these phrases to translate particular
examples.
So that's essentially it.
These are the three components of a
phrase-based translation model.
The little bit more about the trigram
language model.
So these parameters can be trained on
very large quantities of English text.
And the trigram language model is going
to be invaluable in providing a prior
distribution over which sentences are
versus aren't likely in English.
So, here's some notation I'll use
throughout this lecture for the given
sentence that we're try, trying to
translate.
We can extract a set of possible phrases
that are applicable to this particular
sentence, and it'll be useful to use the
following notation for these phrases,
s,t,e.
So s is going to be a start point of the
phrase, and t is going to be the end
point of the phrase, and e is a sequence
of one or more English words.
So one phrase that is applicable to this
particular example is 1, 2, we must, so
let's number these words.
And that says that these two words, wir
mussen, can be translated as we must.
Okay, so words 1 to 2 inclusive can be
translated as we must.
Okay?
so I'm going to use capital P, script P,
to denote the set of all possible phrases
for a particular sentence, okay?
So, these are going to be derived through
entries.
This comes from the fact that we have
some phrase entry in our lexicon, saying
that these two words can be translated as
we must.
And because, these two words, wir mussen,
appear here we can apply this entry.
It's just going to be a little bit more
convenient to think of these phrases once
we have a particular input sentence as
having a start point, an end point and an
English string.
So P is going to be the set of all
possible phrases for a sentence.
So this is going to be a set.
So this might, for example, include 1, 2,
we must.
It might include 1, 3, we must also,
saying that these three words can be
translated as we must also.
it might include an entry saying 6, 6, is
seriously, that would come from an entry
saying that the word ernst, which is
sixth here can be translated as
seriously, and so on, and so on.
This set might again, be quite large, and
notice that many of these phrases will
overlap.
For example, here, I have an entry for
words 1 through 2, and here, I have an
entry for words 1 through 3.
So in summary, big P is just the set of
all possible phrases for an input
sentence, where a phrase is a start point
and an end point and an English string.
So for any phrase p, so let's say p is
equal to 1, 2, we must.
I'll sometimes use the following
notation.
So, sp, tp, ep are its three components.
So s of p is 1, t of p is 2 in this case,
and e of p is equal to we must.
Okay?
And so these three functions are just
pulling out the three different
components of the phrase.
And then, finally, g of p is going to be
the score of the phrase, so this might be
minus 2.5.
And that will come from the original
lexicon, so if we have this entry, entry
saying wir mussen, we must, and g of this
is equal to minus 2.5.
Remember, this is typically log count of
this whole phrase divided by count of the
English.
This is just saying that's the score from
the phrase in the table, okay?
So again, p is going to be the set of old
phrases for the sentence, each phrase is
going to have some scores, some
probability.
And we can easily calculate the set just
by taking our phrase-based lexicon and
applying it to the particular input
sentence that we're trying to translate.