Concepts play an important role in all theories.
Theories in their simples definition are all
statements about reality
that seek to explain or predict the relation
between phenomena.
For instance, the theory of gravity predicts that if I
drop a pen, it will fall to the floor.
A specific predicted result, derived from theory,
we call a hypothesis.
Whenever we visualise these statements this is
called a model.
Usually the arrows and lines in these models
represent hypotheses.
The box on the left in this model represents the
presumed cause, dropping the pencil.
We call this the independent variable. The other
is the presumed effect, or the dependent variable.
If we change our example and look at the theory
that giving someone a gift
causes them to like you better.
Than the independent variable here is giftgiving.
and the dependent variable is how much you are
being liked by someone.
So we can proof or disproof our hypotheses, and
in extension the connected theory,
by actually dropping a pen or giving a gift
and check if the results correspond with the
expected results.
In other words, we test and improve our theories
with use of research.
This can be primary research, where we collect
our own data.
Or by studying the results of others, so called
secondary research.
We have several main means in our field to
gather data.
The first is observation, simply observing the
phenomenon.
Secondly we conduct experiments, where we try
to limit to amount of interfering variables
so we can actually proof a causal relation
between the dependent and independent variable.
We also use surveys, which is a questionnaire
spread amongst a sample of respondents.
The results are usually quantified.
For a more in depth exploration of attitudes we
conduct qualitative interviews.
Finally we study the message itself. This is called
content analysis.
It can be done systematically, where the results
are later quantified.
Or it can be done in a qualitative fashion.
Of course this is the ideal scientific situation. In
reality many theories can’t be tested.
For instance because we can not observe the
presumed relation.
The theory that ‘everything happens for a reason’
might be true,
but we don’t really have access to the methods to
test this.
Sometimes a theory will combine a set of
theories.
For instance The Uses and Gratification Theory:
which is a complex theory that we will discuss
later in depth in this class.
The point for now is that it contains several ideas
about reality.
First of all, people make conscious decisions
regarding their use of media.
Secondly, people are conscious of their media-
related needs.
Thirdly, people select the media that is best
suited to fulfill their needs.
These are only a few elements of this theory, but
my point is
that even though these different statements can
be tested and proven independently,
they are still part of the same theoretical
framework and therefore
collectively labeled as Uses and Gratification
Theory.
So the definition of theory is not as easy as we
first thought.
Some theories don’t even predict anything but
serve more as perspectives on reality
or to sum up an approach.
They tell us it is important to study some aspects
of that reality more thoroughly.
For instance ‘stakeholder theory’ tells us we
should study the stakeholders in any situation
and be aware of their various interests and
agendas.
These perspectives are sometimes called
theory,
but we also use the words paradigms or
approaches,
since they don’t really fit the dominant definition of
scientific theory.
That definition stresses that theories have
predictive value.
And these paradigms or approaches serve more
as view glasses,
which we use to study the world.
They amplify some aspects of reality and guide
our research.