During the sixties critics stood up, they objected
against this linear effect-oriented approach
They argued that many people give a different
meaning to a message than was intended,
but why should that be wrong?
Instead, they focused on the recipients of
communication
and how they give meaning to a message, using
their own unqiue toolkit
with their own backgrounds and experiences,
knowledge, emotions, et cetera.
So in this model, this non-linear model, there is
no wrong outcome,
there is no wrong communication
Everyone gives meaning to a message in there
own unique way
This idea was hardly new.
Scientists had studied the phenomenon of
polysemic messages for a long time.
Polysemic meaning exactly that, different
people interpreting a message in a different way.
According to these scientists each act of
communication relies
on a communication system, without which we
wouldn't understand each other.
The study of these systems iscalled semiotics or semiology,
the so called study of ‘signs’ and ‘signification’.
A sign is basically everything that
communicates something.
A spoken word, a gesture, a glance, a photo, a
cartoon,
a written sentence, a hieroglyph, they are all
signs.
The process of giving meaning to these signs is
called signification.
Without going to deep into this fascinating topic,
it’s important to briefly discuss
the influence of semiotic theories on mass
communication theory.
This approach views communication not as a
linear process but as an exchange of meaning.
The sender puts meaning in a message and the
receiver takes meaning from a message.
Under influence of semiotic theories,
communication scientists became more
interested in the reception of a message
and acknowledged that communication can
indeed have multiple valid outcomes.
Let’s look at this classic model for example,
proposed by linguist Roman Jacobson in 1960.
He starts with familiar elements from Shannon
and Weavers transmission model:
An addresser sends a message to an
addressee using a channel.
He added to the model elements from semiotics
Like the idea that every message refers to
something outside of the message,
which he called context.
Also, the specific form that our communication
takes, for instance a written word,
made up of letters, is called a code.
Successful communication, according to
Jacobson,
can only exist when all of these elements are in
place.
Also, each act of communication has one
dominant function
that relates to one of these elements in this
model.
Let's review these functions that Jacobson
identified.
When the primary purpose of a message is to
communicate
the emotions and attitudes of a sender, this is
called the emotive function.
For instance when I write a love letter to my
girlfriend.
The second function is conative.
If a receiver is directly addressed to do
something specific.
An example is a commercial that tells us to
“buy this flavour of ice cream!”.
The referential or descriptive function
corresponds with the context
and happens when a message primarily
describes a situation.
Perhaps a news report is a good example for
this.
Sometimes the main purpose of communicating
is to keep the lines open,
when we have coffee each week with a friend for
instance.
This is called a phatic function and relates to the
channel.
A poetic function means that the message is an
end in itself,
a painting for example that aims at being a
beautiful and aesthetically pleasing piece of art.
And finally there is the metalingual function,
when we use communication to explain the
codes that we use.
For instance a dictionary.
Another example is the explanation I’m giving
right now,
in which we are discussing concepts from the
field of semiotics.
By focusing on the meaning of a message,
signs, signification and the main function of a
message,
Jacobson has given us a model that is very
different from the transmission model.
It’s also a good starting point to discuss a third
perspective
that offers again a new angle with which to view
our field.