We have just discussed an alternative to the
linear effect oriented approach.
One that looks at message construction and
interpretation,
and leaves room for multiple meanings of a
message.
The third perspective I want to discuss is a
continuation of this line of thought
but shifts the focus to cultural and social
aspects of communication.
This approach deals with how we use
communication to give
meaning to the world around us, construct our
own social reality,
the role of communication in group dynamics
and social interaction.
This perspective makes use of insights from the
field of sociology, social psychology and
anthropology,
where much attention is given to the social
context in which communication takes place.
It sees communication as the means to share
and reinforce ideas,
thereby constantly creating and adapting our
culture.
Also it sees people as social animals,
as such we are constantly involved in social
group dynamics.
To illustrate this approach, let’s examine this
communication model,
proposed by Newcomb as early as 1953.
The model starts out with two familiar elements:
sender and receiver.
Let’s call them person A and person B.
Newcomb thought that the main purpose of
communication is to maintain some sort of
balance, a harmony or equilibrium in a social
system.
He therefore introduced a new element,
the social environment that person A and person
B share.
We’ll call this shared social environment X for
now.
These three elements A, B and X, are all
connected to each other in one social system,
if one element changes, this changes the
relationship of the three.
I will give an example.
Let’s say person A is David and person B is
Shirley.
Shirley and David are colleagues in the same
department,
so this is their shared social environment.
If David quits his job to work somewhere else
this means that they no longer have that same
shared social environment,
their workplace and shared office lunches.
This will inevitably change the relationship
between Dave and Shirley.
Perhaps they’ll decide they enjoyed their lunch
breaks so much
they will now have coffee each month,
even though they don’t work together any more,
thereby going from collegues to friends.
In another scenario David changes jobs within
the company and now becomes Shirley’s boss.
This will also influence their relationship
somehow.
Will they still continue to have friendly lunches
each day?
X can take many forms,
the place you work, political allegiance, a group
you belong to, it can even be a person.
Let’s say X is another co-worker named Ellen.
David and Shirley both like Ellen,
until Ellen and Shirley get into a fight.
Now Davids relationship with the both of them
will change,
he might choose sides or set himself up as a
neutral party.
Regardless of his choice, a new social balance
will be found, and equilibrium restored.
This according to Newcomb is the main function
of communication.
Later other scientists have continued with this
idea, making other theories that
specifically looked at mediated, individual, mass
or group communication.
In later weeks we’ll go more in depth on this.
To go back to the core of Newcomb's model,
and also the core of this third approach:
Communication helps us get along with each
other,
make sense of the social world around us
and enables us to function as social animals.
Therefore, it’s crucial for a stable and healthy
society.
Because without communication, we don't really
feel part of society.
We can’t position ourselves in social reality, for
instance by aligning ourselves with in-groups
or opposing ourselves against out-groups.
Central to this approach is the notion that
people construct a cultural and social reality
by constantly communicating values, attitudes
and ideas.
This idea is sometimes called social
constructionism.