So let’s start by briefly exploring the Classical
World of the Greek and Romans.
We’ll begin in the fifth century before Christ,
Ancient Greece.
Instead of one country we should first recognize
that in these times
Greece was a collection of independent city-
states,
some were at war with each other, and others
were allied.
A growing number of city states was adopting
democratic elements in their governments
such as people’s assemblies, elections, chosen
government officials and such.
Even though many cities still had kings or a
council of nobles,
the political power of citizens was growing,
and with it the need for a better understanding of
the workings of mass communication.
It’s therefore not surprising that the science of
communication thrived in Ancient Greece.
Important historical figures like Socrates, Plato
and Aristotles
were involved in academic debate on the
subject.
But besides being an academic science it was
in this time foremost an applied science.
There were teachers and academies that taught
the main principles of public speaking,
reasoning and persuasion.
Ambitious politicians were wise to learn the
different ways of approaching an audience.
And not only politicians, but also lawyers and
businessmen were schooled in these matters
and made extensive use of it in their field.
Military commanders like Xenophon and
Alexander the Great
had also studied the subject at the feet of
famous philosophers
and used what they learned to keep up moral of
their troops.
So what did the media landscape look like at
this time?
Well, first of all, we already established that
public speaking was important.
Secondly, Greeks made extensive use of
symbolic en figurative communication,
through their art, useable artifacts and
architecture.
Also there was a huge diversity of genres in
theater,
and finally there were many written media,
the alphabet had been rediscovered in the sixth
century and books, scrolls, pamphlets
quickly found a place in the media infrastructure.
Many people, not only the rich and noble, could
read and write
and most cities had one or several libraries.
The most famous library, that of Alexandria,
reputedly contained hundreds of thousands of
handwritten scrolls.
After several centuries the power of the Greeks
dwindled and was broken by the Romans
who themselves adopted many Greek ways.
It’s therefore not surprising that they too learned
and tried to perfect on Greek theories on
communication.
Together Greek and Roman times span over a
millennium of history
and even more if we include the Byzantine
Empire in this
So it’s obviously a huge oversimplification to
discuss all classical thought
on communication in a three minute MOOC
section.
But we’ll try nonetheless,
because their ideas were the basis for scientific
thought on communication
during the Middle Ages and Renaissance.
and therefore in many ways the foundation on
which our modern discipline is built.
For a more in-depth and nuanced picture
I refer to the Little Box of Nuance in the online
environment of this course
and the follow-up opportunities I give in other
sections, like the platform,
and the online community, on Facebook and
LinkedIn