We can make a broad distinction between two
schools of classical thought on communication.
The first school sees communication as a way
to discover the truth of things.
This school started with the famous philosopher
Socrates and his student Plato.
They put a huge emphasis on the role of
discourse
and logical argumentation in the communication
process.
It is called the dialectic method:
which is simply put that logical and rational
discussion
will help us resolve differences by finding out
which viewpoint is true.
Therefore mans ability to reason is paramount
for a civilization to flourish and advance.
Here we have, in a nutshell, the purpose of
communication,
to express and critically weigh the value of
ideas,
and eventually to discard or perfect them in
correlation with their objective worth.
As models go, this one is obviously quite linear.
Good communication is rational communication
that helps us to find ‘the truth’ in ideas.
It' easy to see why so many philosophers, who
were also interested in natural science
and finding out how the world worked, were
attracted to this school of thought.
Later, Medieval monks were also charmed
by this classical idea of communication to reach
the truth.
It was in their opinion a way for pre-Christian
Greeks and Romans
to see the greater truth of God.
So even though they were not Christians,
the writings of Plato and such were copied by
Christian monks and have survived
while so many books of their contemporaries
haven’t.
Usually we only know about these other books
because Plato and such refer and react to them.
This second school of Greek communication
science was called rhetorica.
Derived from the Greek ῥήτωρ (rhḗtōr) which
means "public speaker".
Rhetorica taught the ability to perceive all
means of persuasion in any given scenario,
according to Aristotle in one of his books on the
topic.
So it was very much an applied science, where
the practicality of theories decided their worth.
The main purpose was not to find truth but to
persuade someone,
so essentially to make something seem like the
truth even if it wasn’t.
Proponents of this school were also called
sophists,
and were often attacked vehemently by natural
philosophers like Socrates and Plato,
who above all else searched for the truth.
Later, many sophist writing was purposely not
copied by Medieval monks for this same reason.
Despite the disapproval among natural
philosophers,
rhetorica was extremely popular in the Classical
world.
Not only in Greece but in Rome too
the ability to win people over through speeches
was crucial for political or social advancement.
Caesar, Marc Anthony, Octavian, they were all
trained in
and sometimes wrote about the art of
persuasion.
Usually they had studied the basics of rhetorica
in Greece itself.
Luckily some books on rhetorica did survive.
Most notably those by the Greek philosopher
Aristotle
and the Roman statesman Marcus Cicero.
So what exactly did they teach?
We’ll talk about some basic rhetorical theory in
the next section.