In the Middles Ages the importance of public
speaking grew less.
The political system was completely different of
course so citizens were
basically left out of the political decision making
process.
They couldn’t vote and held little political power,
beyond the power to rebel.
But seeing that the ruler elite were practiced
warriors who wielded deadly weaponry
and impressive armour, both extremely
expensive,
even this was usually not much of a choice.
Although rhetorica was taught in Medieval
universities to a small elite,
it had by no means the importance of classical
times.
Not only was there little to no communication
science in the Dark Ages,
the communication landscape had also changed
drastically
since Roman times. Alfabecy numbers had
dropped rapidly since the decline of Rome.
Almost none could write or read with perhaps
some exceptions
among the ruler and religious elite.
But even among them evidence suggests
readership was not high
and probably very limited to those of very high
stations
or devoted to academic life in a monastery. It
makes sense that written media
became less and less widespread. Important
mass communication channels were
instead oral or figurative in nature. Town criers,
architecture, statues and religious art
were still used to reach a large audience. Coins
were other examples of visual media
that communicated something, typically who
was in charge at a certain time.
The channels of choice were well suited for
communicating who was in power and
and how citizens should behave.
We know the church played an important part in
this and worked hand in hand
with worldly leaders to get this message
through.
Often there were agreements between rulers and
clergymen that at the end
or start of the Sunday mass more worldly news
on taxes, wars
and basically everything citizens should know,
was communicated to the assembled people.
Since most people went to church, this was for
centuries a very effective method
to get a message out amongst the people
if the need arose. Other media also focused on
visual and oral communication.
Plays and theatre still existed but theatres did
not hold the audiences
of thousands as they did in Classical times.
Although written media had almost disappeared
as a means of mass communication,
printed pamphlets with etchings or other
figurative depictions were sometimes used.
Some people might think: they printed
pamphlets? Haven’t we learned
that the printing press was invented in the
fifteenth century by Johannes Gutenberg?
Well, actually, the printing press already existed
long before this time.
However, it was quite expensive to print
something because
basically every page had to be carved out in
wood, stone or metal.
Because the potential audience that was able to
read and pay was small,
it was usually simply not worth it. So what was
this printing innovation of Gutenberg
that everyone always puts so much emphasis
on? It was actually the very cunning
introduction of the cliché, a small letter that
could be put in a box
to make words and sentences.
When the printing was done, the box was
emptied
and new words and pages could be formed.
This innovation made it much quicker and
cheaper to print texts
and is therefore rightly credited as a turning
point in European history
and a huge catalyst for the Renaissance. Of
course this technical revolution would probably
never have had a huge impact if there hadn’t
been an audience to read and buy books at the
same time, which was the result of several long
and complicated historical trends
towards a higher alfabecy level and the rise of a
potential audience with buying power.
Not coincidentally while the mass
communication landscape
started to flourish again with the rise of print
media,
scholars again started to discuss the topic of
communication on a meta level.
So started the Renaissance, not only of art,
science and literature,
but also of our scientific discipline.