It was among other things the rediscovery of
classical texts by
Aristotle and Cicero that started a renewed
interest in
philosophy, art and the natural and social
sciences.
Starting in 14th century Florence, the
Renaissance quickly spread out
to the rest of Europe, paving the way for the
Early Modern time.
This was to a large degree thanks to the new
printing possibilities
that Gutenberg’s invention made possible.
Also, the role of Eastern scholars should not be
overlooked.
In 265 the Roman Empire had been split in a
Western and Eastern half.
When the Western Roman Empire fell in the fifth
century it’s traditions and sciences
lived on in the Eastern Roman Empire of
Byzantium.
In the Dark Ages of Western Europe, Byzantine
scholars still kept extensive libraries
of classical literature and continued studying the
science of rhetorica although it's importance
had declined since advancement in the empire
was much less dependent on
public speaking and more on connections and
status.
Why is this relevant for the Renaissance and
subsequent Early Modern times?
Well, in the fifthteenth century Byzantine power
was crushed by the Ottoman Empire.
The fall of it’s capital Constantinopel in 1453 led
to a huge exodus of scholars
and artists from the Empire into Western
Europe,
feeding the growing intellectual Renaissance
with their work, thoughts and books.
At the same time there was in many countries a
shift of power.
Religiously there was turmoil in Europe because
of new ideas that led to The Reformation and
rise of several new religions. Most successful
was of course the Protestant Church.
The Roman Catholic Church lost its religious
monopoly
and now had to compete for the faith of the
European people.
Closely linked to this was a more worldly power
struggle.
Democratic ideas from antiquity again gained
wide interest.
The introduction of effective weapons like the
crossbow, the longbow and the first fire arms
gave the relatively untrained citizenry more
military power to enforce their claims for more
political power. That any peasant could now kill
a knight with
a well-placed crossbow bolt was a lesson that
wasn’t learned quickly by the ruler elite.
But after several successful uprisings and
military coups,
the idea that it was practical to win the favour of
the masses,
grudgingly became more accepted among the
continents religious and worldly rulers.
It’s not surprising then that next to scientific
thought, arts and literature,
also the printing industry boomed as this graph
clearly shows.
Gutenbergs innovation can be dated in the
1430’s
and at the end of the fifteenth century the
printing industry had already spread out
through Europe and produced more than twenty
million copies.
A century later this number increased to 200
million.
Another century later one billion books were
produced.
We’ll take a closer look at this printing revolution
and its importance for thought on
communication in the next section of our
MOOC.