Welcome in week 3 of our MOOC Introduction to
Communication Science.
Hopefully you have learned something about the
history of communication science and
of course it was a history in a nutshell,
so it would be great if you checked out the
further readings section
we call it a 'Little box of nuance'.
And there is a lively debate developing on
Facebook and on our forum.
As you might remember from our first class,
I have divided the main theories in our field in
three broad approaches,
The first approach is of course the linear effect-
oriented approach
this was for a long time, and perhaps to some
extent still is,
the dominant approach in our field.
It is a perspective that is largely concerned with
the presumed effects
of mass and mediated communication,
or in other words, the power of the media.
I’ll talk about this type of theories and how they
developed in the twentieth century this week.
The second approach was the processing and
signification approach,
which will be the topic for next week.
After that, we’ll discuss the third approach
that focuses on how we use communication to
construct our social and cultural reality.
But for now, we’ll focus on linear effect-oriented
theories
and the developing ideas on the power of the
media.
We left off last week at the end of the nineteenth
century,
start of the twentieth century when scholarly
thought had now accepted the idea
that the media were a political, economical and
social force to be reckoned with.
The eighteenth and nineteenth century had been
riddled with practical examples of their
persuasive powers.
People were surrounded by a rich media
landscape.
Different channels, most noticeably print media
like pamphlets, newspapers and magazines
clamored for attention.
New audience groups had been discovered and
quickly targeted.
The political parties that were born in the
nineteenth century
already had faithful followers at the turn of the
century.
Their party media could count on a returning
audience.
This political press served as a signpost,
telling their voters the viewpoints of the party and
engaging other parties in lively media debates.
Freedom of the press was seen by politicians as
necessary for the media
to fulfill its purpose as a fourth estate,
a political institute and check on government
power,
and therefore press freedom was adopted in
many constitutions all over the world.
It’s not surprising that economists, political
scientists and sociologists
respected the power of and sometimes voiced
an opinion on mass communication.
But it was not yet a full-fledged scientific
perspective. And this would soon change.