After several years of rising political tensions,
World War I erupted in the year 1914.
I have to be careful not to make this in to a
history class,
but it’s important for us to realize the impact of
this war on our topic.
First of all that the war was brewing was quite
apparent for all in the Western World.
Newspapers and magazines gave a lot of
attention to the political and military
manoeuvring on the European continent.
In short, some in the media landscape were
actually campaigning for an aggressive stance
and seemed to be looking forward to a coming
conflict.
Perhaps under the misconception that it would
be a short and relatively clean skirmish
that would restore the preferred balance of
power.
In reality, populations all over the world were
bombarded with patriotic messages and a call to
arms.
Of course this wasn’t the only content in the
media landscape,
but several years later, scientists that studied
what had happened,
noticed the two correlating variables:
media that were campaigning for war and
patriotism
and a motivated, patriotic population, set for war
and many men volunteering to be a soldier
in one of the bloodiest wars the continent had
ever seen.
When the war started, all sides made use of
massive propaganda campaigns.
That's another important concept from our field,
propaganda.
It’s often referred to as ‘one-sided’, ‘biased’ and
‘unobjective’ communication.
Jowett and O’Donnel define propaganda as
‘the deliberate, systematic attempt to shape
perceptions, manipulate cognitions,
and direct behaviour to achieve a response that
furthers the desired intent of the propagandist’.
The world had in 1914 never seen such a huge
‘push’
to influence so many at the same time with use
of mediated communication.
The political and military leaders had perhaps
learned
their lessons from the ancient Greeks and
Romans.
They too wielded the sword of communication
as if it was just one other weapon in their
arsenal,
piercing the mind with its persuasive message.
Again, scholars who studied events directly after
the First World War
noticed a correlation between an intensive
propaganda attempt and
all kinds of effects that were assumed to be the
effect of this propaganda.
It was seen as a reason why soldiers marched
cheerfully in to war.
Why the home front showed such a uniform
support and respect for their military.
Why enemy soldiers decided to defect in mass,
to be imprisoned in military camps for the
remainder of the war.
The importance of World War I on
communication theory is, to put it simple:
it created a huge belief in the power of mass
communication through the media.
We call this the all-powerful media paradigm.