The correlation between presumed cause and
effect during the First World War
had massively increased the belief in the power
of the media.
It was seen by many as an immensely powerful
tool, either for good or ill.
Therefore, not only scientists, but governments
too,
wanted to understand how persuasion through
mass communication worked.
Scientists all over the world received funding to
further study these phenomena,
which of course fuelled research in to this area.
Persuasion through mass communication was a
hot topic,
both as a danger and as a potential solution for
many problems.
Economists were looking for ways to use the
media
to turn the financial crisis of the twenties and
thirties.
Sociologists thought that the media could be
used to strengthen or weaken role patterns,
and they used these ideas to study the
emancipation of women for instance.
All of these scientists basically studied the
question:
how could one guard against the power of the
media?
and how could you harness its potential for your
own benefit?
The underlying notion is of course the premise
that media have a huge effect on the behaviour
of people.
Also commercially the all-powerful media
paradigm thrived.
The advertising industry boomed.
And market research agencies started to study
who read or listened to which medium.
Media organizations needed this info to sell
more ads for better prices.
These commercial market researchers further
added to existing knowledge
on the media landscape and its audiences.
They also standardized techniques to conduct
audience research,
for instance by large-scale surveys which were
then statistically analyzed via a fixed format
and repeated by others all over the world.
The market research industry quickly grew
and maintained its own standards on high
quality research.
Many students who studied these issues in the
university
went on to work in one of the growing research
firms,
using their theories and methods in a more
practical setting,
but with the same dominant attitude prevailing
that media have a potential for great effects on
the behaviour of their audiences.
We call the theory that mass media have a
direct,
immediate and powerful effect on its audiences
the hypodermic needle theory.
Basically the sender ‘injects’ the message in to
the audience with use of the media.
The audience is seen as passive and more or
less unable to resist and immediately affected.
It should be noted that effects, in this
perspective, are seen as:
short term,
immediate,
focused on change rather than reinforcement,
and finally
uniform among the audience,
which means that audience factors are not really
important.
Another word for this theory is the ‘magic bullet’
theory,
another cool name for basically the same
metaphor:
a sender ‘fires’ his message into the brain of a
receiver with use of mediated communication.
Scholars found many examples of the presumed
power of mass communication
and went forth to study these systematically.
The most famous example is perhaps that of the
Martian Invasion of 1938,
when multitudes panicked because of a radio
show in which Mars attacked the earth.
We’ll discuss this example in the next section
of our MOOC,
first from the perspective of the all-powerful
media,
and then from a different angle.