[War of the Worlds]
Ladies and gentlemen, we interrupt our program
of dance music, to bring you a special bulletin
from the intercontinental radio news
At twenty minutes before eight, central time,
Professor Farrell of the Mount Jennings
Observatory, Chicago, Illinois,
reports observing several explosions of
incandescent gas,
occurring at regular intervals on the planet Mars.
The spectroscope indicates the gas to be
hydrogen
and moving towards the earth with enormous
velocity.
Professor Pierson of the Observatory at
Princeton confirms Farrell's observation,
and describes the phenomenon as (quote) like a
jet of blue flame shot from a gun (unquote).
In New York, October 1938, CBS aired a radio
drama about a Martian Invasion.
Director Orson Welles had adapted H.G. Wells
famous book War of the Worlds for the radio.
Most of the show consists of news reports on
the ongoing Martian attack.
It starts slowly with an interview with a leading
astronomer.
Nothing seems very wrong yet, as the interview
is followed by a weather report
and a performance of an orchestra for the
listeners home.
But while the story progresses the reports
become more frantic
and describe several losing battles of the human
army against the Martians.
The captain is conferring with someone. We
can't quite see who.
Oh yes, I believe it's Professor Pierson. Yes, it
is.
Now they've parted. The Professor moves around
one side, studying the object,
while the captain and two policemen advance
with something in their hands.
I can see it now. It's a white handkerchief tied to
a pole . . .
a flag of truce.
If those creatures know what that means . . .
what anything means!. . .
Wait a minute! Something's happening!
(HISSING SOUND)
A humped shape is rising out of the pit.
I can make out a small beam of light against a
mirror.
What's that?
There's a jet of flame springing from the mirror,
and it leaps right at the advancing men.
It strikes them head on!
Good Lord, they're turning into flame!
(SCREAMS AND UNEARTHLY SHRIEKS)
Now the whole field's caught fire. The woods . . .
the barns . . . the gas tanks of automobiles . . .
it's spreading everywhere. It's coming this way.
About twenty yards to my right . . .
Ladies and gentlemen, due to circumstances
beyond our control,
we are unable to continue the broadcast from
Grover's Mill.
Evidently there's some difficulty ...
This example is often used to illustrate the
power of mediated communication
since the broadcast reputedly led to mass
panic.
Newspapers report that thousands ran scared in
to streets,
and we get the idea that complete
pandemonium ensued.
This would of course indicate exactly what the
magic bullet theory predicts:
immediate, short-term, uniform effects among
the masses.
immediate, short term, uniform effects among
However, scientists that studied this incident,
most notably Paul Lazarsfeld and Herta Herzog,
actually found evidence that suggested a more
nuanced picture.
First of all, many people had tuned in long after
the show started,
thereby missing the introduction that explained
it was a show.
More importantly, they found that contextual
factors had influenced the collective reaction.
It was 1938 and the news media had informed
their audiences
on the potential of an upcoming war with
Germany.
So people were forewarned that a war might
happen.
Research showed that some who panicked
actually missed the part about the Martians
and assumed it was a German invasion that
took place.
Another important finding was that newspapers
had probably
exaggerated somewhat the 'widespread panic',
that followed the broadcast.
Reality was perhaps less sensational:
yes hundreds of thousands were frightened to
some degree,
but in reality most of them had not acted on
their fear,
no evidence of hysterical screaming masses in
the streets,
no suicides by people who wanted to stay out of
the hands of the Martians.
Later Lazarsfeld again criticized the magic bullet
theory,
this time together with Berelson and Gaudet
when they disproved the hypothesis that voters
were persuaded to vote for Roosevelt
because of his extensive campaign.
These studies are examples of a line of
questioning
in to the all-powerful media paradigm by
scholars.
They were systematically testing the magic
bullet hypothesis
and had been unable to reproduce the presumed
effects in an experimental setting.
Also scientists found that often in cases of
presumed huge effects in real-life scenarios,
like the Martian Scare of 1938,
there were many other variables to take into
consideration, besides media influence.
Because these critical notions were the result of
a long list of scientific studies.
we call this paradigm,
the powerful media put to the test.