While scientists all over were adhering to the
minimal effects hypothesis,
a different contrary trend led to a so-called
rediscovery of the powerful media paradigm.
One important reason for this
were the many presumed effects of
communication during the Second World War.
Not only historians but sociologists too pointed
at the concerted propaganda efforts of both the
Allied and Axis forces.
Specifically the situation in Nazi Germany that
had caused so many to agree with
and later not object to Hitler’s policies was an
important theme for study.
This new paradigm that formed,
the Powerful Media Rediscovered
was slightly more nuanced then the older
Powerful Media paradigm.
Scientists had learned from the studies of
Lazarsfeld and Hovland and such
that direct, immediate and uniform effects were
difficult to prove.
But ever since World War II there was a growing
body of scientific work forming
that suggested strong long-term, indirect and
personal effects.
New theories on powerful media were more
nuanced than the older ones,
and saw the effects more in terms of
reinforcement than actual change.
Not only scientists objected to the minimal
effect theory:
popular belief in the Powerful Media Paradigm
remained strong, and only grew after the war.
Many people working in the advertisement,
political campaigning or in the media industry
could not come to terms with the minimal
effects thesis
and added anecdotal evidence that further
supported the idea of a powerful media.
World War II propaganda had in the popular eye
been extremely influential
even though scientists were still arguing this
because it had helped create a huge social
support for the war effort.
The idea that the media had failed pre-war
Germany was also apparent.
Why hadn’t the Fourth Estate stopped the rise
of Hitler?
What was the use of a check on government
power
if it didn’t stop something like this from
happening.
These and other instances were media owners
misused their powers
led to a Commission on Freedom of the Press
to investigate the democratic role of the media.
In 1947 they published their report, and it's still
the basis for our modern thought today on this.
They concluded that yes, like the Fourth Estate
model,
the press is crucial for a healthy political
system,
because they serve as a platform for opinions of
the people
and they serve as a check on government
power.
However, unlike the Fourth Estate model,
which included that the media should be free of
any constrictions,
the Commission proposed:
a) that in order for the media to serve the people,
there should be guidelines that govern media
behaviour.
and b) that the basis of these guidelines should
be a feeling of social responsibility.
This is why this model is called the social
responsibility model.
and c) The Commission stated that every
political institute needs checks and balances,
therefore also the media can’t be completely
without restrictions.
There is room for government interference in
extreme cases.
d) however, it is preferable to avoid extreme
measures,
therefore the media should govern themselves
through a system of a professional codes of
ethics,
upheld by a self-imposed regulatory body.
It is this Social Responsibility Model that is in
fact dominant today.
Each country has of course its own variation,
but usually there is some rules that media
organizations adhere to.
And there is some sort of committee made up of
media professionals
that don’t hold any official power but media
organizations agree
that this court can fine them
and give other sanctions when the professional
code is breached.
The introduction all over the world of this new
system of media governance clearly shows that
despite the fact that scientifically the issue was
under debate
the powerful media idea was still widespread.
This belief further increased with the rise of
television.