The final paradigm I want to discuss with you
this week
is a compromise between the minimal effects
and powerful media perspectives.
Combining elements of both models the
negotiated media effects model states that
media and communication in general,
not only mass, the focus is broader than that,
have a potential for great power.
Effects can be short term, direct, immediate,
after one-shot exposure et cetera.
However, more often, strong and enduring effects
are based on long term, repeated exposure
where the content reinforces rather than
changes the audiences beliefs.
This perspective combines the insights of
political en economical scholars with those of
psychologists, sociologists and even cultural
anthropologists,
looks at human development and sees
persuasion as something continuous.
Something that is not to be avoided, because
we need it to function.
It can’t be avoided without losing that which
connects us with each other.
Many studies with children were now done,
to find out more about the role of communication
during crucial development phases.
Also, many societal problems, like crime,
prejudice, aggressive
and anti-social behaviour were now linked to
communication,
either as a cause or a possible solution. And
often, both.
Tries to merge qualitative and quantitative
methods.
For instance by backing qualitative statements
with quantitative data, thereby aiming to
measure the subjective.
Looks at all kinds of effects.
Agenda Setting for instance is a theory that
proposes
that the media don’t tell us what to think, but
what to think about.
The media agenda therefore influences the
public agenda,
if the marriage of some celebrity is much
discussed in the news
it will probably feature higher on the public
perception as well.
The media tell us which items are important,
where important things happen and why.
The amount of attention given to environmental
pollution by the media for instance
can cause a higher percentage of people
thinking about this subject
and a higher percentage of people evaluating
environmental pollution
as a serious and important problem.
Frames define problems, shape possible
solutions and basically help a person
deconstruct a message in a particular way.
For instance, when we are talking about
pollution of the environment,
we can have many different angles to approach
this topic.
We can talk about the big pollutors in the world,
or what you as a consumer can do,
or we can go down into the basic facts and
figures of global warming.
These are all different frames that will lead to a
different deconstruction of the message.
In these photo’s the same news event,
the tearing down of Saddam Hussein's Statue,
is depicted.
The frame is however quite different,
thereby probably changing how we deconstruct
the message.
We can see that these types of theories no
longer focus on the intention of the sender
but rather on message construction and
deconstruction.
So no longer the linear effect oriented approach
but a focus on the construction and the
reception of a message.
On processing and signification. We are going
to continue with that topic, next week.
I hope to see you then!